<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>assistive-technology on mattoppenheim</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/assistive-technology/</link><description>Recent content in assistive-technology on mattoppenheim</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/assistive-technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bendlabs single-axis bend sensor</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2021/12/30/bendlabs-single-axis-bend-sensor/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2021/12/30/bendlabs-single-axis-bend-sensor/</guid><description>Using the Bendlabs 1-axis bend sensor with an ESP32 board This post explores using a more tactile and sensitive type of flex sensor than I&amp;rsquo;ve used so far. This is part of my ongoing flex sensor assistive technology project.
The flex-sensor is the bendlabs 1-axis flex sensor.
In this post I show how I interfaced this sensor with an Unexpected Maker feather S2 board and started logging data from it. This board uses the ESP32 S2 MCU.</description></item><item><title>Accessing Smartbox Grid 3 using Python and win32gui</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2020/10/08/accessing-smartbox-grid-3-using-python-and-win32gui/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2020/10/08/accessing-smartbox-grid-3-using-python-and-win32gui/</guid><description>Summary Smartbox&amp;rsquo;s Grid 3 communication software creates two windows containing the words &amp;lsquo;Grid 3&amp;rsquo; in their titles, even though you can only see one. If you are trying to interact with this software using your own program, you need to make sure to access the window that you intend to.
Problem I wrote some Python code to detect the use of Grid 3 or Tobii&amp;rsquo;s Communicator software for this project, to visually show when somebody who uses eyegaze technology interacts with the software.</description></item><item><title>Communication Matters Conference 2019</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2019/09/12/communication-matters-conference-2019/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2019/09/12/communication-matters-conference-2019/</guid><description>I attended the 2019 Communication Matters Conference in Leeds on Monday. I presented a poster on three of my assistive technology projects using the BBC micro:bit and gave a &amp;rsquo;lightning talk&amp;rsquo; - 15 slides, auto advancing every 25 seconds. I wrote the PowerPoint presentation using Libreoffice on my Linux distro. Just before giving the talk I realised I had not tested it in Windows, which the conference PC was running with.</description></item><item><title>Using the microbit to control switch access software</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2019/06/24/using-the-microbit-to-control-switch-access-software/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2019/06/24/using-the-microbit-to-control-switch-access-software/</guid><description>What is switch access software Many disabled people use specialist software to create speech or to interact with the environment (e.g. turn on lights). Some are unable to use keyboards or mice to operate this software, so use a variety of &amp;lsquo;switches&amp;rsquo;, such as push buttons. These buttons act like keys on a keyboard, or pretend to be a mouse click.
I took some hand held video of a switchable software package which enables speech to be created.</description></item><item><title>Using Python to detect activity in Sensory Software's Grid 2</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2018/03/01/using-python-to-detect-activity-in-sensory-softwares-grid-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2018/03/01/using-python-to-detect-activity-in-sensory-softwares-grid-2/</guid><description>Update: March 2018. This work is being submitted to the Communications Matters conference.
Following on from the eyeBlink post, with the help of Fil at Beaumont, I modified the algorithm I&amp;rsquo;m using to detect when the Grid 2 or Grid 3 software is being used. The image below shows Sensory Software&amp;rsquo;s Grid 2 software being used to construct a sentence. The new text appears in the white area at the top of the window.</description></item><item><title>eyeBlink - enabling natural two way conversation with somebody who uses an eyetracker</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2017/07/14/eyeblink/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2017/07/14/eyeblink/</guid><description>It can be difficult to tell when a student who uses an eye tracker to operate their communications software is actively using the software. So the temptation is to go and look over their shoulder. The Head Technologist at Beaumont College asked if it is possible to have a light flash to indicate when the communications software is being used. This makes for a more natural two way conversation. You talk to the student and you see the light flashing, so you know that a reply is being composed.</description></item><item><title>CD player for the visually impaired</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2017/01/15/cd-player-for-the-visually-impaired/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/2017/01/15/cd-player-for-the-visually-impaired/</guid><description>This blog details a method to allow somebody who is visually impaired to easily listen to their CD collection again. My Mother lost her eyesight through macular degeneration. She has a decent collection of classical music that she built up over a few years. But she can&amp;rsquo;t see well enough to easily use a CD player anymore. On top of that, her mobility is restricted. I bought her a Roberts Concerto 2 CD player and radio designed for the visually impaired.</description></item></channel></rss>