<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>fet on mattoppenheim</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/fet/</link><description>Recent content in fet on mattoppenheim</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/fet/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Logic level converter between an Arduino Uno and micro:bit using a FET transistor</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/logic-level-converter-between-an-arduino-and-microbit-using-a-fet-transistor/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/logic-level-converter-between-an-arduino-and-microbit-using-a-fet-transistor/</guid><description>Summary We can use a single FET transistor with two resistors to make a two way logic level converter to interface e.g. Arduino Uno and a micro:bit.
The problem I need to interface a micro:bit to an Arduino Uno, connecting the RX and TX pins of the Arduino to tabs on the edge connector of the micro:bit. The Arduino Uno has 5V logic levels. The micro:bit has 3V logic levels. The 5V signals from the Arduino Uno may damage the micro:bit.</description></item><item><title>Voltage controlled current source</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/voltage-controlled-current-source/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/voltage-controlled-current-source/</guid><description>Design I needed a voltage controlled current source (VCCS) to test some current limiting devices. A friend who knows far more than I about analog electronics recommended using a power op-amp, which is an op-amp capable of outputting a high current. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have one of these to hand, so used a regular low power op-amp to drive the gate of an N-type MOSFET. I think that a power op-amp is just a regular op-amp with some meaty FETs inside and a package capable of disappating more heat than a regular puny op-amp.</description></item><item><title>Switching a 5V DC motor with a microbit.</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/switching-a-5v-dc-motor-with-a-microbit/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/switching-a-5v-dc-motor-with-a-microbit/</guid><description>This post shows how to use a BBC microbit to control a 5V fan or DC motor using a FET switch. The circuit shows how we can use a transistor to control a device that needs more current than the microbit can supply.
This project uses a 5V voltage from a USB power bank.
Only connect 5V to the USB connector on the microbit - not the battery connector or the edge connector.</description></item><item><title>200V piezo crystal driver</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/200v-piezo-crystal-driver/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/200v-piezo-crystal-driver/</guid><description>Spoiler alert: I got the driving circuitry to behave as planned, but I could not feel the crystal vibrate.
The idea is to use the tiny crystals used in piezoelectric motors to create an array of dots that can be made to vibrate under the area of a finger tip. This will be used to create a tactile display that can be felt. The initial aim would be an array of these crystals under an area the size of your fingertip.</description></item></channel></rss>