<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>microbit-2 on mattoppenheim</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/microbit-2/</link><description>Recent content in microbit-2 on mattoppenheim</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/microbit-2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using micro:bits to send data to and from an Arduino wirelessly</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-microbits-to-send-data-to-and-from-an-arduino-wirelessly/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-microbits-to-send-data-to-and-from-an-arduino-wirelessly/</guid><description>Summary We can use microbits to act as a wireless bridge between an Arduino Uno and a PC. One micro:bit connects to the Arduino. The second connects to the PC. Data can be passed to and from the Arduino serial port through the micro:bits.
The problem A friend has an Arduino based instrument that he wants to communicate with from his PC wirelessly. Why? I don&amp;rsquo;t ask why. He&amp;rsquo;s bigger than I am.</description></item><item><title>Logic level converter between an Arduino Uno and micro:bit using a FET transistor</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/logic-level-converter-between-an-arduino-and-microbit-using-a-fet-transistor/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/logic-level-converter-between-an-arduino-and-microbit-using-a-fet-transistor/</guid><description>Summary We can use a single FET transistor with two resistors to make a two way logic level converter to interface e.g. Arduino Uno and a micro:bit.
The problem I need to interface a micro:bit to an Arduino Uno, connecting the RX and TX pins of the Arduino to tabs on the edge connector of the micro:bit. The Arduino Uno has 5V logic levels. The micro:bit has 3V logic levels. The 5V signals from the Arduino Uno may damage the micro:bit.</description></item><item><title>Using the micro:bit to detect electrical current</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-the-microbit-to-detect-electrical-current/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-the-microbit-to-detect-electrical-current/</guid><description>This blog is an ongoing record of using the micro:bit to detect electrical current.
Idea The micro:bit has a magnetometer on the board. When a current flows through a wire, a magnetic field is produced. We can use the magnetometer to detect this.
This is part of an energy conservation project for classroom use.
Summary The magnetometer on the micro:bit is used to detect the change in magnetic field produced in the mains cable to a hair dryer when it is turned on and off.</description></item><item><title>micro:bit edge connector expansion board retainer clip</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/microbit-edge-connector-pcb-retainer-clip/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/microbit-edge-connector-pcb-retainer-clip/</guid><description>The problem I use PCB expansion boards to plug my micro:bit into for a recent project. The micro:bit has connection pins printed along the edge of the board. This is called an &amp;rsquo;edge connector&amp;rsquo;. Have a look here if you are not familiar with the micro:bit board. This edge connector plugs into an edge connector socket on the expansion board. The two components can be easily separated.
As I give the finished devices to other people to use, I need a way to stop the micro:bit from being easily removed from the expansion board.</description></item><item><title>micro:bit v1 with yotta - removing build warnings</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/microbit-v1-with-yotta-removing-build-warnings/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/microbit-v1-with-yotta-removing-build-warnings/</guid><description>problem Running yotta build with the micro:bit v1 C tools produces screenfulls of depreceation warnings, such as:
warning: dynamic exception specifications are deprecated in C++11 [-Wdeprecated]
This makes it hard to find the error messages with the reason why the build failed.
solution Tell the C++ compiler not to include depreceation warnings.
instructions Add the compiler flag -Wno-deprecated to the CMAKE_CXX_FLAGS_INIT options in the file toolchain.cmake.
File location:
&amp;lt;project&amp;gt;/yotta_targets/bbc-microbit-classic-gcc/CMake/toolchain.cmake&amp;gt;/yotta_targets/bbc-microbit-classic-gcc/CMake/toolchain.cmake Line before:</description></item><item><title>Setting up a micropython editor with the BBC micro:bit v2 on Linux</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/setting-up-a-micropython-editor-with-the-bbc-microbit-v2-on-linux/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/setting-up-a-micropython-editor-with-the-bbc-microbit-v2-on-linux/</guid><description>This post follows on from my blog post that shows how to set up the mu-editor in Linux for v1 of the micro:bit. This blog post is here:
https://mattoppenheim.com/2021/01/05/setting-up-mu-editor-with-the-bbc-microbit-on-linux/
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get the mu-editor to work with micro:bit v2. This was frustrating as I wanted to check some existing code ran on v2 of the micro:bit as well as start to use some of the new feautures on board.
I solved this by following a tip from a comment on my first post.</description></item><item><title>Setting up mu-editor with the BBC micro:bit v1 on Linux</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/setting-up-mu-editor-with-the-bbc-microbit-on-linux/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/setting-up-mu-editor-with-the-bbc-microbit-on-linux/</guid><description>I recently set up an installation of Debian 10 and set up a tool chain for programming the BBC micro:bit with micropython. I&amp;rsquo;d forgotten some of the stumbling blocks I had the last time I did this, so am recording them here. Hopefully, this post will help you avoid them.
I use to represent the user name that I log in with.
The instructions in this blog get you set up to work with the micro:bit v1 using mu-editor.</description></item><item><title>Automating loading micropython code to the BBC micro:bit in Linux</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/automating-loading-micropython-code-to-the-bbc-microbit-in-linux/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/automating-loading-micropython-code-to-the-bbc-microbit-in-linux/</guid><description>Introduction When I edit micropython for a microbit project, I want the code to automagically load onto the microbit each time that I save the code. Then I want to see any messages from the microbit displayed. I worked out a toolchain that does this under Linux.
I summarise the toolchain in the next section, then go through each step in more detail.
For the examples in this post, I am editing a file called &amp;lsquo;feeder.</description></item><item><title>Real time accelerometer display from three BBC Micro:bits</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/real-time-accelerometer-display-from-three-bbc-microbits/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/real-time-accelerometer-display-from-three-bbc-microbits/</guid><description>How to plot real-time sensor data from three BBC micro:bits.
Please find a video showing this in action below. On the screen to the right of the juggling clown, you can see the accelerometer data. Each BBC micro:bit has a three-axis accelerometer in it. I get the averaged acceleration value from all three axes from each micro:bit. On the screen, three are three traces, one for each micro:bit. As the boards are juggled, the accelerometer values are sent by radio to a receiver micro:bit connected to the computer.</description></item></channel></rss>