<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>3d-printing on mattoppenheim</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/3d-printing/</link><description>Recent content in 3d-printing on mattoppenheim</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/3d-printing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>micro:bit edge connector expansion board retainer clip</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/post/2021/07/microbit-edge-connector-pcb-retainer-clip/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/post/2021/07/microbit-edge-connector-pcb-retainer-clip/</guid><description>The problem I use PCB expansion boards to plug my micro:bit into for a recent project. The micro:bit has connection pins printed along the edge of the board. This is called an &amp;rsquo;edge connector&amp;rsquo;. Have a look here if you are not familiar with the micro:bit board. This edge connector plugs into an edge connector socket on the expansion board. The two components can be easily separated.
As I give the finished devices to other people to use, I need a way to stop the micro:bit from being easily removed from the expansion board.</description></item><item><title>3D printing face shields on a Creality CR10-Mini</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/post/2020/04/3d-printing-face-shields-on-a-cr10-mini/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/post/2020/04/3d-printing-face-shields-on-a-cr10-mini/</guid><description>Like a lot of folk right now (mid Covid-19 lockdown), I&amp;rsquo;m using a 3D printer to produce face shields. I started from scratch and with little experience of using a 3D printer. This post will detail some of the issues I had and my solutions, in the off chance that this information could help somebody else.
Please see my HSE manager testing one of the completed face shields in the picture below so you know what I am talking about.</description></item></channel></rss>