<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>bbc-microbit on mattoppenheim</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/bbc-microbit/</link><description>Recent content in bbc-microbit on mattoppenheim</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mattoppenheim.github.io/tags/bbc-microbit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using a microbit to control a servo motor</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-a-microbit-to-control-a-servo-motor/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-a-microbit-to-control-a-servo-motor/</guid><description>Subtitle: Making things move a microbit at a time
In this post I explain how I set up and operated a small servo motor that runs directly from the same 2xAAA battery pack that powers my microbit. I then explain how to operate a servo motor that requires a 5V power supply from the same microbit, using a transistor as a voltage level converter for the control signal.
Introduction I set up a small servo motor for a project to make an automated guinea pig feeder.</description></item><item><title>BBC micro:bit guinea pig timed feeder instructions</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/bbc-microbit-activating-a-servo-motor-using-a-timer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/bbc-microbit-activating-a-servo-motor-using-a-timer/</guid><description>This blog post is the instructions on how to use a timed servo motor circuit that I lashed up as part of a guinea pig feeder for a friend.
The hardware details can be found here: here
Software is on my GitHub site here
The need A friend wanted something to open a box of food to feed his guinea pigs. The box needs to open after an adjustable time.</description></item><item><title>BBC micro:bit wrist holders</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/bbc-microbit-wrist-holders/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/bbc-microbit-wrist-holders/</guid><description>With my handshake project, a microbit and AAA battery pack need to be worn on the wrist. They can be vigorously shaken. I don&amp;rsquo;t want the equipment flying off! So what can I use that will hold the microbit and batteries safely in place and is comfortable and safe to wear?
I tried a couple of armband holders aimed at iPods recently. Both of them are suitable for housing a BBC microbit and a AAA battery pack.</description></item><item><title>Powering the BBC micro:bit with a 5V power bank</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/powering-the-bbc-microbit-with-a-5v-power-bank/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/powering-the-bbc-microbit-with-a-5v-power-bank/</guid><description>I had an interesting question to a blog post I made about running a DC motor from a microbit. The blog post is here. I am pleased that anybody reads my blogs.
Doesn&amp;rsquo;t applying 5V to the microbit board exceed the voltage spec?
When we connect the board to our laptops or PCs, we apply 5V to the board through the USB connector. Sometimes I run the board from a USB power bank.</description></item><item><title>Running handShake in administrator mode to operate Grid 3</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/running-handshake-in-administrator-mode-to-operate-grid-3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/running-handshake-in-administrator-mode-to-operate-grid-3/</guid><description>Sensory Software&amp;rsquo;s Grid 3 is a popular communication software package, running in Windows. Naturally, I would like handShake to be able to operate this software through the software keystrokes that handShake generates. To get Grid 3 to respond to a software keystroke, I have to &amp;rsquo;elevate&amp;rsquo; the base.py script which runs on the communication device to run as an Administrator.
There is a second solution. I can use a Freetronics Leostick USB dongle as a pretend keyboard and have this generate keystrokes that appear as coming from a physical keyboard.</description></item><item><title>Connecting the BBC micro:bit to Windows and adding code to it</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/connecting-the-bbc-microbit-to-windows-and-adding-code-to-it/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/connecting-the-bbc-microbit-to-windows-and-adding-code-to-it/</guid><description>This page details how to connect the BBC micro:bit to Windows then install a pre-written program to it. This guide was written to support some of my &amp;lsquo;how-to&amp;rsquo; guides for assistive technology devices I made using the BBC micro:bit.
Author: Matthew Oppenheim
email: matt.oppenheim@gmail.com
GitHub site: https://github.com/mattoppenheim
Summary Connect the microbit using a micro USB cable from the microbit to the Windows device. You do not need a battery pack for the microbit.</description></item><item><title>Switching a 5V DC motor with a microbit.</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/switching-a-5v-dc-motor-with-a-microbit/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/switching-a-5v-dc-motor-with-a-microbit/</guid><description>This post shows how to use a BBC microbit to control a 5V fan or DC motor using a FET switch. The circuit shows how we can use a transistor to control a device that needs more current than the microbit can supply.
This project uses a 5V voltage from a USB power bank.
Only connect 5V to the USB connector on the microbit - not the battery connector or the edge connector.</description></item><item><title>Using udev to remove the need for sudo with the BBC Micro:bit</title><link>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-udev-to-remove-the-need-for-sudo-with-the-bbc-microbit/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mattoppenheim.github.io/using-udev-to-remove-the-need-for-sudo-with-the-bbc-microbit/</guid><description>A comment on this post hinted that there is a way to remove the need to use &amp;lsquo;sudo&amp;rsquo; when interacting with the BBC Micro:bit on Linux. So I left a comment asking how to do this, which the author kindly answered:
The way to make sure there is no need for root permissions to access USB device (like a connected micro:bit) is by creating a file in the `/etc/udev/rules.d/` directory with proper config.</description></item></channel></rss>